Finding Aid for the R.M. Ballantyne Papers LSC.0321
UCLA Library Special Collections
R.M. Ballantyne papers
1876-1893
UCLA Library Special Collections
Ballantyne, R.M. (Robert Michael)
LSC.0321
1.0 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
R.M. Ballantyne (1825-1894) was a apprentice clerk with Hudson's Bay Company in Manitoba, Canada. He requested a wilderness post, and was sent to posts along the north shore of the St. Lawrence (1846-47). His recollections were published in 1848 and titled Hudson's Bay; or, every-day life in the wilds of North America. He wrote more than 90 books, many of them adventure stories. He was also a draftsman and water-colorist who exhibited at the Royal Scottish Academy, and he illustrated many of his books. The collection consists of manuscripts, correspondence, and a scrapbook with pictures of Ballantyne, clippings about him, and an article copied by Westley about Ballantyne.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Harriett S. Weaver, 1986.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942303533606533
Biography
Ballantyne was born on April 24, 1825 in Edinburgh, Scotland; became apprentice clerk with Hudson's Bay Company in Manitoba, Canada; requested a wilderness post, and was sent to posts along the north shore of the St. Lawrence, 1846-47; following his return to Scotland in 1847, a woman who had enjoyed Ballantyne's letters to his mother offered to finance a private printing of his recollections; this led to the publication in 1848 of Hudson's Bay; or, every-day life in the wilds of North America; wrote more than 90 books, many of them adventure stories; he was also a draftsman and water-colorist who exhibited at the Royal Scottish Academy, and he illustrated many of his books; publications include Snowflakes and sunbeams; or, the young fur traders (1856) and Ungava: a tale of Esquimaux-land (1858) and An author's adventures, or personal reminiscences in bookmaking (1893); he died February 8, 1894 in Rome.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of manuscripts, five letters from Ballantyne to various persons, a letter by Ballantyne to the Reverend J.C. Westley, and a scrapbook with pictures of Ballantyne, clippings about him, and an article copied by Westley about Ballantyne. Manuscripts include Dusty diamonds cut and polished: a tale of city-Arab life and adventure; The garret and the garden: or, low life high up; Hunted and harried: a tale of the Scottish Covenanters; Post haste: a tale of Her Majesty's mails; Under the waves: or, diving in deep waters; and The walrus hunters: a romance of the realms of ice.
Authors, Scottish -- 20th century -- Archives.; Manuscripts for publication; Ballantyne, R.M. (Robert Michael), 1825-1894--Archives.
- [Correspondence], v.d.
  - Letters, n.d.; 4 items. (Box 1)
  - Letter to Reverend J.C. Westley. Harrow, May 5, 1883.; 6 leaves. (Box 1)
- [Manuscripts], v.d.; 2 boxes (1 linear ft.)
  - Hunted & Harried. Nisbet, 1892. (Box 1)
  - Dusty diamonds..., 1893.; 378 leaves. Holograph. (Box 1)
    General note
    Sadleir no.106.
  - The garrett and the garden: or, low life high up. n.p., 1886.; 121 leaves. Holograph. (Box 1)
  - The walrus hunters..., 1893. (Box 2)
  - Posthaste..., 1879.; 2 p.l., 386 leaves. Holograph. (Box 2)
    Sadleir no.121.
  - Under the waves..., 1876.; 383 leaves. Holograph. (Box 2)
    Sadleir no.129.